Hello, I'm Colin Sanders. I go by Dr.
Xor.
I'm not a real doctor, but I am the guy
that solved Mr. Beast's million-dollar
Super Bowl puzzle.
This video is going to be very different
from any other video I make. Obviously,
solving the puzzle was a big deal for me
and I'm still wrapping my head around it
and in a lot of ways. While I am
absolutely addicted to solving puzzles,
they're not my whole life and I was
thinking a lot about this opportunity
and what some of the different pieces of
my life have in common.
And a really different idea occurred to
me, which is what you're about to see.
In this video, I'm going to tell three
riddles, each in the form of a story and
by the end, I hope to make a point that
is very important to me, tell you where
that leads and hopefully you, the
viewer, might be interested in what
comes next.
The first story is about a boy who was a
good friend. He was always encouraging,
a good listener, and generally got along
well with everyone he met.
One day, a bunch of his friends decided
to form a club. They called it the best.
And for the fun of being dramatic, they
held a meeting to give everyone a
special title. Some of these were
personality traits, others were skills.
For example, the strong, the fast, the
loyal, the fixer. Last but not least,
because the boy I mentioned was the
closest friend to so many in the room,
the best club voted to call him the best
friend. The next day, word got out and
plenty of other kids were interested in
joining the best. So, they held a second
meeting and gave out dozens of new
names.
But already by the third day, so many
children had started asking to join the
club that the original members decided
to hold a secret meeting. First, they
argued about who they should let in.
Then, they started getting into how to
earn names and who should keep their
current ones. Just as the conversation
started to seem a little more laid-back,
the boy they called the best friend
remembered something. He asked the group
if he could invite just one more person.
They rolled their eyes and asked who it
was, and he replied in a slightly
smaller voice that he would like to
invite his best friend.
The tension from earlier snapped. The
strong one thought that he was the boy's
best friend, which offended the fast one
who thought the strong was his best
friend. And in a moment, everyone began
fighting over who their best friend was
supposed to be and who didn't deserve
their name.
And then, as kids do, calling each other
bad names. "Evil traitor."
Finally, they decided it was all the
boy's fault that they were unhappy. They
said, "You lied to us, and if you're not
our best friend, you can go find some
other club."
So, the boy came up with a new name,
left the club, and never looked back.
To answer the riddle, tell me this. What
was the boy's new name?
The second story is about a boy who
wanted to be a soldier.
When he came of age, he joined a group
of special forces that called themselves
The Chosen. And even though this gave
him a sense of purpose he'd always been
looking for, he had met a girl a month
before boot camp in his hometown.
And they had spent every day at the
beach together.
On the last day before he departed, the
girl had brought a camera and taken a
picture of their favorite spot on some
high rocks near the edge of the ocean.
When she gave the young man the photo,
he felt such a strong connection to it
that he promised they would meet there
again. Now, the young man was a natural
during combat and survival training, but
towards the end of the first year,
something odd happened. He expected to
be promoted to squad captain, but the
commander said that he was too
distracted by the girl back at home. So,
the young man stopped talking about the
girl to any of his fellow soldiers.
At the end of the second year, the
commander caught him writing letters
after hours to the girl
and said that he would refuse to promote
him a second time. The young man stopped
writing to the girl. He trained harder
and harder, eager to get his first
assignment in the field. And towards the
end of the third year, the general of
the chosen paid a visit. On a day where
it was pouring rain,
the general summoned everyone to the
courtyard. The man heard his name called
and stepped forward proudly.
But the general wasn't holding a metal.
He was holding a photo of the beach
stolen from the man's bunk. And in front
of the entire camp, he announced that
the girl the young man had been talking
to was a spy. The air hummed
mysteriously. Before the young man could
respond, lightning struck. The picture
in the general's hand caught fire and he
threw it into the air screaming as it
disintegrated into ashes. Officers
barked orders and everyone scattered for
cover.
Believe it or not, the young man had
seen this coming and didn't move an
inch.
He waited until the courtyard had
cleared, sighed, and took one last look
around the campus.
The next day he resigned. He had looked
at that photo, his reminder of the girl,
for a thousand nights.
And whether she was some kind of spy or
not, on the horizon, in the distant
clouds above the ocean,
her camera had captured a lightning
bolt.
To answer this riddle, tell me this.
What was the true nature of the soldier
and the girl?
The third story is about a man who
wanted to be a writer. He was applying
for a job with the biggest news agency
in the city and he had been lucky enough
to have a talk with one of their
journalists who got him an interview
that went very well. And the company
offered him a job if he could impress
them by writing a story about himself
within three days. So the man began to
write about when he was very young and
formed a club with his friends. And then
about his time training in a special
forces unit. By the end of the first
day,
he had a draft ready and sent it in.
The person that responded by email asked
him if he would like to come work in the
office to see what it was like.
So the second day, he arrived and was
shown to a temporary desk and a
computer.
He wrote well into the afternoon adding
details and as much flair as he could
and then proofreading until he was sure
that the story was complete. Then a
writer he hadn't met before joined him
to review. But to the man's
disappointment, when the writer had
finished reading, his opinion was,
"I don't think the audience is going to
believe this story."
So, for the next 2 hours they went
through the text.
The man listened carefully as the writer
pointed out missing context,
contradictions, and even a few factual
errors here and there that the man was
ashamed to have forgotten. For the third
day, the man showed up as early as he
could before dawn. He noticed that some
of the men and women who had already
made it into the office gave him nervous
glances as he passed. When he reached
his desk, there was a tall woman in a
dark suit waiting for him and the
computer was gone replaced by blank
reams of paper, a pile of pencils, and a
hand sharpener. The woman told him that
if everything he had written so far was
true, the company was interested in
producing a documentary of his life. She
was going to help him write the story
one more time from scratch and watch his
process to try and figure out why the
previous day's writer had needed
convincing.
About 4 hours passed. The man's hands
were covered in graphite, his back
started to ache, and the room felt cold.
Five more hours passed. The woman was
stopping him constantly, adjusting every
sentence, asking for info, and sometimes
crumpling entire pages. Six more hours
passed. The man pushed himself through
broken pencils, paper cuts, thirst, and
then hunger until finally, late in the
evening, the story came to an end.
He waited in exhaustion as the woman
stared at the empty space after the
final period.
Eventually, she said,
"It's good,
but you still haven't convinced me that
it's real.
I think it'd be best if you worked
somewhere else.
To answer the riddle, tell me this. What
do the news really want?
So, that's it. Three stories, three
riddles. Don't worry about solving them
yet. I'm going to need to give you a
little bit more information. But, I'll
get to the point of this video. To solve
a million-dollar puzzle,
I worked with a team of strangers that I
never met before, and we didn't think we
were going to win, obviously. So,
beforehand, we casually agreed to split
the money
And that was what I did. And I want to
tell you the reason it was
easier than it should have been
to give away most of a million dollars.
Because it wasn't the moment I found out
that I won,
or getting into a Rolls-Royce, or a
private jet, or even shaking Mr. Beast's
hand.
It was a moment a little bit later in
Greenville
where someone pulled up a chair,
and I looked up at this room full of
people with huge smiles on their faces,
and they asked me to tell them about
something that I love the most.
Technically, it's just talking about
puzzles, right? This crazy, wacky hobby
that doesn't have anything to do with
real life.
Except I have such an unusual history
and so much exposure to this stuff that
has all led up to this point. And it is
very real for me. It has much more to do
with my life than most people would
realize at first, I think. Maybe that's
true for anything people do for fun for
long enough, right? That it it defines
them in some way.
Solving puzzles is something that has
started to come out in everything I do
from washing the dishes to watching
birds in my backyard.
Those are birds or something.
And when I talk about enjoying puzzles,
I'm also talking about other people and
how they think, what they've discovered,
and how they do things that seem
impossible all the time.
The point is, I realized sitting in that
chair
that having a positive experience,
sharing things that are important to me
with a group of people
Woo, it's getting windy. Talking about
things that are important to me
with a large group of people
was something that I had assumed would
never happen again for the rest of my
life.
So, Mr. Beast, Salesforce, Lone Shark
Games, my team, really thank you to
everyone that made that happen. Now,
I've really got to get out of this wind.
I hope you enjoyed this little
experiment of mine. I think of puzzles
as stories. So, I do want to make videos
about riddles and puzzle games and
unsolved mysteries that are out there.
But, I want you to get a sense of what
it feels like to approach these things
and sometimes solve them. I'd like to
tell you more about what all of this
means to me and how puzzles are designed
and about all of the crazy people you
can meet behind some of this stuff. And
I might make videos about other things,
books and movies, music, birds,
any of the random things that catch my
interest from month to month because I
love to find patterns in just about
anything and talk to people about all of
those things.
And I think those conversations are also
going to be a lot more like solving
puzzles than you might expect. I might
create some puzzles, too, but my intent
is not to hang them over your head and
say, "Ha ha ha, are you as smart as you
think you are?" And I hope that you can
surprise yourself with some of the
things you can do. And you know, maybe
win something every once in a while.
But, if you win something, I hope that
it is a reward for taking the journey
into someone else's shoes rather than
just solving a really hard crossword and
Sudoku. I have some ideas for what I
want to do on YouTube and Twitch as well
as a bigger project that I hope will see
the light of day in a year or two. So
again, I hope you enjoyed. Thanks for
watching. And let's go solve some
puzzles.
>> Ah.